<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"> <channel> <title>Harmen Stoppels</title> <description></description> <link>http://stoppels.blog</link> <atom:link href="http://stoppels.blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/> <item> <title>Jacobi-Davidson example</title> <description>Let's take a look how the Jacobi-Davidson algorithm targets interior eigenvalues of a Poisson matrix.</description> <pubDate>Sun, 11 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate> <link>http://stoppels.blog/posts/jacobi-davidson-example</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stoppels.blog/posts/jacobi-davidson-example</guid> </item> <item> <title>Harmonic Ritz values visualized</title> <description>A hopefully insightful visualizion of harmonic Ritz values versus ordinary Ritz values.</description> <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate> <link>http://stoppels.blog/posts/harmonic-ritz-values-visualized</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stoppels.blog/posts/harmonic-ritz-values-visualized</guid> </item> <item> <title>Interior eigenvalues in Jacobi-Davidson</title> <description>From the Arnoldi method we know that Ritz values tend to converge to exterior eigenvalues; similar behaviour is observed in Jacobi-Davidson. This is an issue when restarting the method: a Ritz value close to a specified interior target is not necessarily a good approximation of an eigenvalue in that neighbourhood; the Ritz value might as well be on its way to an exterior eigenvalue, and in that case we would not want the Ritz vector to be retained at restart. An alternative is to use harmonic Ritz pairs.</description> <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate> <link>http://stoppels.blog/posts/interior-eigenvalues</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stoppels.blog/posts/interior-eigenvalues</guid> </item> <item> <title>Towards the next eigenpair in Jacobi-Davidson</title> <description>After removing a converged Ritz vector from the search space, we must ensure that new expansions do not bring it back. In practice this means updating the correction equation so that these directions are deflated.</description> <pubDate>Sat, 03 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate> <link>http://stoppels.blog/posts/towards-the-next-eigenpair</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stoppels.blog/posts/towards-the-next-eigenpair</guid> </item> <item> <title>Non-Hermetian eigenproblems in Jacobi-Davidson</title> <description>Non-Hermetian matrices do not necessarily have orthogonal eigenvectors for distinct eigenvalues. So far we have relied upon this property when shrinking the search subspace. Fortunately we can work with the Schur decomposition to tackle this problem.</description> <pubDate>Sat, 03 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate> <link>http://stoppels.blog/posts/non-hermetian-eigenproblems</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stoppels.blog/posts/non-hermetian-eigenproblems</guid> </item> <item> <title>Shrinking the search subspace in Jacobi-Davidson</title> <description>Once an approximate eigenvector has converged, we must remove it from the search space, so that other eigenpairs can be found. Also, when a search subspace becomes too large, a restart is necessary. This also requires removing vectors from the search space. Fortunately, shrinking the search subspace is easier in comparison to IRAM.</description> <pubDate>Fri, 02 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate> <link>http://stoppels.blog/posts/shrinking-the-search-subspace</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stoppels.blog/posts/shrinking-the-search-subspace</guid> </item> <item> <title>Options in Jacobi-Davidson</title> <description>In my previous post I showed the defining property for Jacobi-Davidson, but it turns out that there is a lot of freedom in the remaining parts of the algorithm. For instance in how to initialize it; this post will be about exactly that.</description> <pubDate>Fri, 02 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate> <link>http://stoppels.blog/posts/options-in-jacobi-davidson</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stoppels.blog/posts/options-in-jacobi-davidson</guid> </item> <item> <title>Jacobi-Davidson</title> <description>As part of Google Summer of Code I'm implementing several iterative methods for linear systems of equations and eigenvalue problems in Julia. Up to now I have studied Jacobi-Davidson and have a poor man's version working. The first post is about my notes on the method.</description> <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate> <link>http://stoppels.blog/posts/jacobi-davidson</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stoppels.blog/posts/jacobi-davidson</guid> </item> <item> <title>Compile-time primes</title> <description>Anyone who has seen C++ template meta-programming must have come across the compile-time prime number generator by Erwin Unruh. Since then the language has evolved and provides a very readible alternative. In this post I'll touch on both the classical and modern approach.</description> <pubDate>Fri, 10 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate> <link>http://stoppels.blog/posts/compile-time-primes</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stoppels.blog/posts/compile-time-primes</guid> </item> <item> <title>Hello world</title> <description>Every now and then I'll post some findings in programming and math, ranging from solutions to Project Euler exercises to numerical methods in partial differential equations.</description> <pubDate>Thu, 09 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate> <link>http://stoppels.blog/posts/hello-world</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stoppels.blog/posts/hello-world</guid> </item> </channel> </rss>